software engineering radio episode 29
concurrency part 3
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to this episode
of software engineering radio this is
concurrency part 3 however before we
start talking about concurrency I want
to I want to comment on some of the
comments we got from from you listeners
specifically on those that complained or
hinted at some of our sound problems
so we got several messages that said you
know contents grade and all of that but
your your sound is not too good at times
there is echo voices are not loud enough
if there are two people on the podcast
one loses voice is loud the other voices
rather quiet we know about these
problems we're aware of these problems
and we're working on that the problem in
our case is that we are as you know we
were a team of people who record those
things so we have we don't just have one
recording site where we can optimize
things we have various people who recall
things we have various software packages
various operating systems so everybody
has their own personal challenge in
recording a good sounding podcast
episode we are of the aware of the
problem and we are working on that I've
also been purchasing additional
recalling equipment with preamps and all
that however keep in mind that it will
probably still not sound like a really
professional recording this is really
hard to do in this kind of distributed
setting where we record our episodes and
so we've already recorded a couple of
episodes so those will have the usual
not-so-great sound quality but the
forthcoming episodes
probably from episode 34 or something
onwards will have better sound quality
okay so that's all for that one let's go
on with the topic for this episode which
is concurrency part 3 welcome to a third
episode on concurrency when we focused
in the first two episodes on the very
basics of concurrency this time we will
talk about how to build highly scalable
servers especially we will talk
about the reactor pattern and how it is
used and how servers can be built to be
highly scalable so if you take a look at
application servers you can divide them
into two different kind of application
servers Mikkel I guess you have an
opinion which kind of application server
is better suite or how we can yeah
divide the application server area for
this discussion here I would
differentiate between event-driven
servers and and data-driven servers for
an event-driven server I would see a
large number of concurrent requests from
users or other systems and for
data-driven applications this is
typically the domain of batch processing
data analyzes heavily algorithmic
centric and so I know that you there's
no black or white
the server is not only event-driven
but for this discussion and
to better distinguished assistance I
would make this distinction and in the
later discussion we focused mainly on
the event driven servers because for the
data driven servers
different patterns are applicable to
optimize them yeah so could we say most
of the servers we have in our daily
business web servers application be
applications servers they are all
event-driven application service is that
correct yeah to a large extent I would
say they are avenged driven the way we
use them as as web servers as
general IT infrastructure servers are
typically event rather than I would say
okay before we discuss how to build them
what are the major problems what are the
factors that lead to low performance or
scalability on these event-driven
application servers yeah some of the key
problems that I see and
I learned us from Dutch mate when we did
middleware optimizations is that dynamic
memory allocations for example are
generally dynamic resource acquisitions
lead to a high percentage of overhead in
the algorithms in communicating in in
dispatching events further there is a
synchronization overhead on shared
resources when you have concurrency and
thirdly it's the waiting time on
blocking synchronous calls so all three
areas are important to address the
fourth one is like resource shortage
when there's really no resource
available anymore but I don't consider
that so important because it's then we
have a failure anyway and to deal with
resource shortage when there are no
resources available anymore this is a
really hard topic and I know almost no
application or no server that can
properly deal with that mm-hmm okay
I'm not sure if we already defined the
terms and previous episodes but I guess
we should divide them or define the word
scalability performance and throughput I
mean these are the most important
characteristics of application service
and they mean different things could you
just give us a few words on this yeah I
would first refer to architecture 2
episode
where we have discussed this briefly but
for here
scalability
well what what is scalability to us when
doing upscaling so when increasing the
load on the system ideally we want to
have the same through port we want to
have the same quality properties for the
individual requests as we had for the
lower number of requests but
realistically it is not like that so in
the best case we have a linear
degradation
and in the worse case which is then
where we are not satisfied as when the
system would perform really poorly at a
certain limit for example with ten users
the system works fine with hundred we we
realize some degradation and with
thousand users the system would just not
react anymore in any timely a manner
that would be poor scalability but if
the system would just be somewhat slower
with thousand users then we would be
satisfied we would
have a scalability on this system mm-hmm
but there's also the scalability you
know this scale out where so scale up
thing how if you add Hardware how you do
it if you add a
additional server to your cluster system
or at an yeah faster much faster CPU or
whatever the bottleneck is yeah the
scalability is also whether you can
actually
change your configuration to deal with
higher system loads I mean you're not
scalable when your system cannot be
extended and so you you run into this
problem of poor throughput and poor
performance
really early when your system cannot be
extended soso extendibility is kind of a
property necessary for scalability was
this what you were hinting at yeah
exactly I mean this scaling up or
scaling out thing is exactly that how
you modify your hardware or your system
to add more performance to your system I
mean you have to waste basically you can
buy a faster CPU or hard drive or
whatever the bottleneck is and the other
way is to add well a new server to the
server system to a cluster system with
more than one server add a new CPU or
whatever an additional Hardware hard
drive and it still has to scale out in
this case and how we measure scalability
here not only performance is important
but also the through part we is slightly
different than then performance or is is
contained and in performance figures and
also latency and a jitter of requests
all those properties
qualify a high quality system from a
poor quality from a poorly behaving
system mm-hmm can you just drop a few
words on the on through port late
latency and jitter what does this mean
actually yeah you could measure when you
when you talk about the measure units
and you can explain throughput latency
and jitter so in case of throughput this
is how many requests per second get
through your system and throughput
doesn't tell you anything about latency
latency is
what was the delay incurred
the delay imposed on the system when the
request arrived until it was served okay
I mean taking those
measurement points you can also think of
other measurement points and jitter is
like the difference in the delay that is
introduced by the system when there's
large jitter there in it for example one
request might take in one case and one
millisecond and in other cases it takes
a complete second until it gets served
it's so important for systems that are
interacting with users because then the
users don't know what to expect from the
system when it's generally slow when
every request when every mouse click
takes two seconds it's okay for the user
but it when it's really fast and when
there is a good user experience and
suddenly it drops then the user doesn't
know what to think of the application
and it's is confused and my click twice
three times because they he thinks he
missed the button or things like that so
here it's also important to stay within
some bounds of jitter okay
and I guess if you try to optimize one
and not all the other characteristic
hairs are optimized to as well or maybe
there is contradiction weary sometimes
yeah it's like balancing forces it's
like balancing these three properties
together with with other quality
attributes like maintainability and
flexibility so you have to find
trade-offs and and find a good
configurations that fulfill your
requirements okay what can we do to
optimize all this
yeah I would start off with the reactive
design
mainly described by the reactor pattern
so when we have an event of an
application
reactive or event-driven design is the
best way to deal with those requests
with those events the reactor pattern
allow us to wait for multiple events
from multiple sources
using a single or multiple threads and
and the key property of the reactor is
that it separates the waiting and
dispatching of events from the handling
of events so you have event handlers
that you register with the reactor and
say well I want to wait for this kind of
event on this event source and then the
reactor puts that into its list of event
sources that it waits on and the typical
call in current OSS is the Select call
that is used to wait on on those events
mm-hmm reactor can be used in a single
or in a multi-threaded environment in a
single threaded environment of course
it's more easy and the design is more
clear and a single threaded
reactor implementation is very well
suited when you want to avoid all the
difficulties associated with concurrency
and so the single threaded reactor
implementation avoids synchronization
overhead it and minimizes the dynamic
memory allocations because you just have
no con currency and that is often a good
alternative so a single-threaded reactor
design is a good alternative to
concurrent applications
but on the downside and you might have
not the high CPU utilization that you
require or so you don't use your
resources optimally in some
circumstances and having multiple CPUs
and having this application the server
application the salt being the sole
application running on a CPU on a multi
CPU machine you don't gain the benefits
of having multiple CPUs so out there are
reasons and and in situations when you
want to have a multi-threaded reactor of
course and you said it doesn't cure is
the multi-threaded version of reactor I
guess there are different ways how to
use it multi-threaded in simple
multi-threaded application servers and
there are models implemented like thread
per connection or thread per requests
and thread per connection you would have
for every client connection you would
have a dedicated thread that could even
log on a read call and then just serve
this request but of course if you have
multiple connections if you have really
many connections you have a resource
bottleneck so your tenders then and and
you should use the reactor same is with
threat to request spawning a threat
every time our new request arrives also
doesn't scale really well what you want
to have and what is much better is a
flexible association between connections
requests and threats and
here thread pools come into play mm-hmm
but
first going back to to what's really
difficult in a multi-threaded rare
reactor environment this is the
synchronization overhead firstly
and secondly and the concurrency often
demands memory allocations dynamic
memory allocations for example for the
queues because anything that you
exchange between two
two threads must be allocated on the
heap and not understand of course you
could reallocate
eagerly aquire to talk in the terms of
poster 3 and you could equally acquire
the memory and then share it between the
two threads but often for simplification
reasons this is not done and the source
of therefore source of overhead and the
third part is that you a third issue
challenge is that you consume quite many
resources as in the case of thread per
requests or thread per connection the
number of open connections and the
number of threats can can be quite high
what kind of measures do we do to go
with this
firstly I mean now I'm going to iterate
through a list of patterns and concept
for example thread specific storage can
be used when you have
data that is thread the cific or thread
logo basically avoid to have shared
resources
another key pattern is like reader
writers locks to minimize
synchronization overhead when there are
more readers of a variable of a
synchronized or protected variable then
then writers and and in other words the
the read access occurs more frequently
than the write accesses can you I am not
sure if we already did it in the second
episode of concurrency we didn't define
reader/writer lock so I guess did we no
I don't think we we discussed them yet
so the yeah having this this key
assumption that the read accesses are
much more seldom you
know the write success you can having
having this assumption that the right
accesses are much more seldom than the
read accesses you know that a read
access doesn't really harm when when it
occurs inherently so you can allow many
concurrent
reads on your data but as soon as there
is a write you should make sure that
there is no more read on the on the data
so the wreath doesn't block at all just
too right yeah the the read doesn't
block unless there is a write
concurrently acting okay and then the
the readers will be just cute and until
the the write is finished and then they
can start reading again and
similar it is for the rider the rider is
blocked as long as there are still
readers reading it and now of course you
you can juggle a bit with priorities of
who is more important the the writer or
the reader who has to wait for the other
but there are some some typical
resolutions to the this that a writer
because it's more seldom and it's more
important that you have current or
actual data that you give the writer a
higher priority than the readers okay I
guess condition variable is pretty close
there yeah a condition variable allows
you to suspend a thread while waiting
for certain condition to be true and so
a condition variable is typically
provided by the operating system
or by the API programming API and its
associated as the name says with a
condition that you define and
that condition is typically measured or
dependent on a set of shared variables
and the shared variables of course they
need to be protected by some locks so
you have variables that are shared
between multiple threats and
you have a lock associated you have the
condition variable and so the condition
variable is used to synchronize and
recheck the condition when there are any
changes on those variables and the
thread weights on a certain condition to
be true and the other threats that don't
wait on the condition but that
manipulate the variables they then
signal the condition variables so that
does one thread
potentially waiting for a condition can
then we check the condition and as soon
as the condition is true it can proceed
in its with the data being locked so the
condition variable itself frees the log
as so as long as the thread waits until
the signal arrives this is kind of
complicated but by the whole bike that I
explained some the key ideas of it okay
okay back to the list of things we can
do to avoid yeah resource problems using
the reactor pattern
I guess thread pose is a huge topic
there too yeah thread pools and memory
pools pooling and generally in general
is important here and the thread pools
and memory pools they allow to minimize
the acquisition overhead and limit the
resource consumption and
in the case of thread pools a thread
pool
creates
normally a set of threads in advance
uses those threads so
individual parts of the application can
require a thread from the thread pool
and release it back to the thread pool
the threads themselves they wait
typically on on a condition variable
until their
service routine is set on which they
should execute okay so we avoid the you
know the overhead of creation or
creation of threads on the fly but we
have of course the
the problem that we have this pool full
of your resources blocked all the time
right and so there's an various
strategies on how to
[Music]
destroy threats when there are no longer
used or how to acquire new threats
create new threats when the existing
number of threats are not sufficient
anymore when there's a higher demand and
those properties on how much to Eagle II
acquire how much to - later than acquire
on demand threats this is a
configuration option and really depends
on how and when you optimize your system
okay of course the the pools are not
only used for threats especially in
server applications or development you
have this for almost all resource as you
have many parallel threats so pooling is
very important server side yeah
so an another important thing learned
from the design of concurrent and highly
scalable servers was to minimize the
usage of queues to avoid memory
allocations and to boyd to avoid jitter
so queues are really good when you want
to decouple between two threats and in
the pipes and filters
the sign pattern when you apply it in a
concurrent setting you have the queues
as pipes between the filters and the
filters are executors typically in
individual threats so here it's inherent
but i would say as long as you can avoid
it as long as you don't really require a
pipes and filter architecture a
concurrent one then try to avoid queues
because
firstly
you don't minimize any
availability or unavailability figures
saying when my system is busy I have a
q-and-a queued and just gets filled as
long as it's not available but any queue
will be full at one point in time so you
just delay the
failure and you don't really avoid a
availability failure but isn't this
exactly the point from the beginning of
our show I mean if you have I wouldn't
say many but sufficient number of queues
you optimize for throughput but not for
that latency so you you have to charge
every time you you use it if one or the
other is better and if you want more
throughput off your server or more
latency yeah the but the throughput can
be also reduced when you have dynamic
memory allocations on your queues so
this I would say it's a trade-off
between better decoupling your system
and having individual threads for single
tasks and versus having
better latency and smaller jitter and
maybe somewhat higher through much
constant and
but now coming coming back to the
reactor and using the reactor in
multi-threaded environments
when you use the reactor in a
multi-threaded environment it's
advisable to use a thread pool as we
just learned to to have the resources
the consumed resources under control but
then we have all kinds of problems for
example how should multiple threads wait
on a singer
and shared set of resources and here the
leader followers patterns come comes
into play the the key of this pattern is
that it nicely
organizes and manages how the threads
pick up work from the from the event
sources and how they can then later for
example wait dedicated on dedicated
responses that come through the event
source and it works like that that you
always have a leader as long as thread
is waiting on the event source and that
the other threads are take over the role
of a follower and the followers again
wait on a condition variable
until they are signaled to either pick
up their response that are they are
waiting for or to become the leader and
the leader is the only one who actually
reads from the event source and when the
leader for example
recognizes that this event is not
designated
for for its event handler for its
execution that in then it can signal the
followers to deal with that special
event okay so is this kind of a pipes of
our pipes and filters architecture or a
man getting it wrong no no it's pipes
and filters is different you have
multiple threads that are
generally not distinguishable from each
other as long as they didn't execute any
code yet and so they they are all
equally important they have all the same
roles initially but when they wait on
the event source they take on they take
on temporarily the role of a leader or a
follower but then later they don't they
don't really exchange the data between
them on as the leader gets a response
that is designated to a follower that is
the only interaction among them
only in this case but else they pick up
the work and do the work and go back to
the event source to listen on it and and
receive the next events okay we spoke a
lot about the problems with reactor and
all this design stuff but of course
there are benefits too
yeah I mean the the benefit of using the
reactor in a multi-threaded environment
said here you can really use make use of
multiple CPUs and you have typically a
higher CPU utilization so that you may
even want to monitor you see your CPU
utilization so that it doesn't grow you
out of control and that
you can also run other
monitoring applications or other
applications on that server as well and
that it doesn't grab all your resources
available when there's a high load from
the users or from other systems that
trigger events on your system okay okay
I also heard about a synchronous i/o
that is used and server development to
speed things up can you say a bit on on
this -
yeah asynchronous i/o is is really an
excellent thing it's
doing thing a things asynchronously not
waiting on a read even when you know
that the read is can be performed
without waiting but that you don't even
have to wait till the read finishes you
can use in a sort of a synchronous i/o
of some operating systems for example
those that are POSIX conformant and be
notified on the completion of events so
instead of event arrival as in the case
of reactor
with asynchronous i/o you wait for the
completion of events and the pattern
associated here is the proact or pattern
which tries to make the things a bit
more easier tries to give the developer
of programming model on how to use the
asynchronous i/o
API of the operating system still and
nevertheless I find asynchronous i/o
programming very complicated very
tedious I mean it's it's proven that
it's highly efficient but it's so
complex that it's
well I I try to avoid it yet and and
always try to
use the reactive model and select
operations instead of using the
asynchronous i/o because it also like
it's not available on every operating
system or the api's are different so you
have a small porting issue here in C++
for example you can use ACE the adaptive
communication environment by Daksh MIT
and this hides some of the complexity
nevertheless it's it's quite complicated
ok another pattern associated in this
domain is the asynchronous completion
talk on a CT for associating responses
with requests so when you send the
request asynchronously to another thread
or to another peer process whatever and
you get the response back and you want
to associate it with the
request that you send so when you have
multiple responses outstanding
you can then associate this one specific
response to the request that you
initially send ok so it's basically I am
an idea or something like that yeah it's
an ID and you can use pointers with some
limitations or just other unique means
to identify
a piece of data essentially okay to sum
it up we now talked about how to build
scalable servers especially how to use
the reactor pattern and all the problems
that might be involved there and the the
resource usage pooling thread pooling
it seems still a complicated thing would
say the same well it's yeah the patterns
alleviated a bit but nevertheless
multi-threaded server programming is
something really difficult and so I
lately heard some some interviews from
other people some some podcast and the
common opinion and and the common trend
when you look at application servers is
that concurrency is best shielded from
the application developer into the
infrastructure
so you you don't see many problems that
way but of course the the programming
model and and the concurrency model is
then fixed and you don't have so much
space for optimizations for for
general-purpose web servers and
general-purpose application servers this
is mostly okay but when you want to
squeeze out the last resources and the
last bit of performance through port or
when the general-purpose application
servers are not sufficient you have to
go and
through the pain of building those
systems and maybe even with multiple
threads yeah maybe one last tip for me
here there are very good application
service out there that are open source
all that each Abi's stuff the the tomcat
and the Apache server you know we have
the great chance now to look into this
servers how they are built and it's much
easier than a few years ago to get
knowledge the stuff if you're really
interested in how to build application
servers thanks for listening to another
episode and software engineering radio
we hope you liked it in case you have a
comment leave us a comment at our site
se - radio dotnet bye bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think software
engineering radio wants to thank Henning
poly for the intro and outro music as
well as Lipson for providing the
bandwidth this episode of se radio as
well as all other episodes is licensed
under Creative Commons license see the
software engineering radio website for
details